And what? So well again we're starting at דף ע׳ Daf Ayin
and we're top right right at the top. So מאי שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa? What is the
difference, what is the reason that in the first case I mean
it's a pretty obvious difference but the גמרא Gemara is just asking
that in the first case of the משנה Mishna you forget that
it's שבת, Shabbat, you bring for each שבת Shabbat you transgress no
matter how many מלאכות melachot you do, and the second case you
forget the מלאכות, melachot, you bring for the number of מלאכות melachot
you do individually. So what is the difference? I mean it's a
very straightforward answer but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רב ספרא Amar Rav Safra so says רב ספרא, Rav Safra, כאן
ידיעת שבת הוא פורש וכאן ידיעת מלאכה הוא פורש. kan yedi'at Shabbat
hu poresh v'kan yedi'at melacha hu poresh.
Very simple. In one case if you were told, "Hey, it's שבת,
Shabbat, what are you doing?" "Oh, right." And then you would have
stopped. So therefore that was the first case. So therefore your mistake
was about שבת. Shabbat. If you had known שבת Shabbat you wouldn't
have done it. So it was one mistake and if you had
been told one thing you would have stopped doing all the מלאכות
melachot you had done. If you were told it's שבת Shabbat you
would have stopped. In the other case you'll stop doing it because
you're told, "Hey, you can't do that, that's a מלאכה." melacha. So
and then for each separate מלאכה melacha it would have been a
different thing that would have made you stop and therefore each one
of those is a different act and is a different category. Okay,
very straightforward. Now interestingly רב נחמן Rav Nachman will see challenges this
and says something else which to me sounds pretty much the exact
same. But let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman
said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, כלום פורש משבת אלא משום מלאכות? klum
poresh miShabbat ela mishum melachot?
When I say to you, "Hey, what are you doing? It's שבת."
Shabbat. And then you stop doing what you were about to do
or what you were in the middle of doing. The reason you're
stopping is because you know two things. You know that it's שבת
Shabbat and you know what you're doing is a מלאכה melacha on
שבת. Shabbat. You had forgotten that today was שבת Shabbat but you
know you're not allowed to cook on שבת. Shabbat. So when you
stop doing it you stop doing it because it's שבת Shabbat and
because it's a מלאכה. melacha. And in the other case when I
said and when I said, "Hey, you can't cook on שבת, Shabbat,
you can't cook, you know, what are you doing? That's a מלאכה."
melacha. So in that case וכלום פורש ממלאכה אלא משום שבת? v'klum
poresh mi'melacha ela mishum Shabbat?
When I tell you, "Hey, what are you doing? That's a מלאכה."
melacha. Then you realize you're not going to do it but you
already knew it was שבת. Shabbat. So you're not doing it because
of two reasons: because it's שבת Shabbat and because I reminded you
that it was a מלאכה. melacha. So he says the act that's
what's making you separate is always two factors: your knowledge that it's
שבת Shabbat and your knowledge this is informed, this is forbidden. You
have just been informed about one of those factors that you had
forgotten. So why so he says I don't get it, in both
cases the reason you're not doing it is because you now know
both of those things. Again it's very hard to understand what's bothering
him. That might be very true that the reason you're not doing
it is because you now know both of those things but the
reason I was about to do it was because I was ignorant
about one of them and the question is, you know, which one
was I ignorant about. So let's see what his answer is. His
answer sounds to me like it's the same thing just rephrased. So
here's what he says. אלא אמר רב נחמן Ela amar Rav Nachman
says רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
קרבן דחייב רחמנא אמאי? korban d'chayev Rachmana amai? Why is the תורה
Torah telling you you bring a קרבן? korban? אשגגה. Ashgaga. So because
of your error. So you made a mistake. התם
חדא שגגה. Hatam chada shgaga. When you forget it's שבת Shabbat even
if you did many מלאכות melachot you made one error. Your error
was you forgot it was שבת, Shabbat, that was one error. הכא
טובא שגגות הוינן. Hacha tuvah shgagot havinan. In this case, thank you,
you made many errors. You made an error that you didn't remember
that you're not allowed to cook and you made an error you
didn't remember you're not allowed to plant. So for each different מלאכה
melacha category you made a different error. So again to me it
sounds like it's basically all saying the same thing. In the first
case you forgot it was שבת, Shabbat, that was one mistake. One
way of saying that is had you remembered it was שבת Shabbat
you wouldn't have done everything you did. Another way of saying it
is you forgot it was שבת, Shabbat, it was one error and
therefore one קרבן. korban. In the other case you knew it was
שבת Shabbat and every separate מלאכה melacha was a separate error. So
the first way of saying it is had you been told it
was a מלאכה melacha you wouldn't have done it and that's true,
each different מלאכה melacha you needed to be informed separately. And the
other way of saying it is you made all those multiple errors
because for each מלאכה melacha you made an error. So to me
it's two ways of saying the same thing. I really don't understand
what the challenge is and what the response is. We will see
at the end of today's דף daf why the different articulation might
have a subtle difference in a particular case. Okay, but basically they
are both for now they are both saying essentially the same point.
That if you forget it's שבת Shabbat it's one mistake, if you
forget the מלאכות melachot it's a different mistake for every מלאכה melacha
that you have forgotten. Now חייב על כל מלאכה ומלאכה. chayev al
kol melacha u'melacha. Now we get to the fact that you are
חייב chayev for each separate מלאכה melacha category. So again if you
if you water and fertilize and prune you only bring one even
though maybe you made three mistakes because each one of those you
know was a different thing that you should have known was forbidden
but nevertheless it's all the mistake within one category. But if you
if you watered your plant and cooked then you bring two חטאות
chataos they're from two separate categories.
So the גמרא Gemara says חילוק מלאכות מנלן? chiluk melachot minalan? Where
do you know this idea all together that you bring separate חטאות
chataos for separate מלאכות? melachot? Because as I said to you the
general rule is let's say it's פסח Pesach and I first eat
a nice loaf of bread and then an hour later I eat
a cookie and you know three hours later I have some pasta
and it's all I all at the same. I forgot that whole
day that it was פסח. Pesach. How many חטאותes chatas do I
bring? One. It's one sin. I did multiple times eating חמץ chametz
without remembering in between, which would have divided them into separate קרבנות.
korbanos. So I bring one, even though I did it multiple times,
it was one sin. Even though once it was חמץ, chametz, once
it was bread, once it was pasta, and once it was cookies.
So here too, I violated שבת Shabbos three times. Once I violated
it by cooking, once by watering my plants, once by, I don't
know, building a house. Okay, three times I violated. Why is that
three חטאותes? chatas It should be like eating three different types of
חמץ. chametz. What is—where do we know this idea of חילוק מלאכות,
chiluk melachos, that each מלאכה melacha is a separate category, a separate
type of a violation on שבת Shabbos and a separate קרבן? korban?
מנלן, Minalan, where do we know this from? אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel
says, שמואל Shmuel אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, מחלליה
מות יומת. mechaleleha mos yumas.
Those that desecrate it shall be surely put to death. It's a
double language, מות יומת, mos yumas, a double language. התורה ריבתה מיתות
הרבה על חילול אחד. Hatorah ribsa misos harbe al chilul echad.
You can die many times for one violation. Now, as you can't
really die more than once, but okay. But the point is, and
as the גמרא Gemara more or less asks, what do you mean?
What does that tell you about קרבנות? korbanos? האי במזיד כתיב, Hai
bemezid ksiv, that's talking about willful violation, מות יומת. mos yumas. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אם אינו עניין למזיד, im eino inyan lemezid,
it can't be talking about מזיד. mezid. We don't need the פסוק
pasuk for that, also like I said, תוספות Tosafos points it out,
you can't die multiple times. But anyway, דכתיב, deksiv, כל עושה מלאכה
יומת, kol ose melacha yumas,
anybody that does מלאכה melacha shall be put to death. So we
already know that it's punishable by death. So therefore, why does it
have to say מחלליה
מות יומת? mechaleleha mos yumas? So תנהו עניין לשוגג, tenehu inyan leshogeg,
to tell you this idea of multiplicity not by a מזיד mezid
case, but by a שוגג, shogeg, an unintentional case, that therefore there
are multiple punishments you can have for violating שבת, Shabbos, and therefore
for each separate מלאכה melacha is a separate קרבן. korban.
You're saying מות יומת mos yumas is
double, is that what you're saying?
Yes, because מות יומת mos yumas is double.
Is he saying מות ימותו mos yamutu which would have been more
plural?
No, he could have just said ימות yamut or something, I don't
know, יומת, yumat, like the other פסוק, pasuk, yeah.
Is in your case about פסח Pesach the same as the other
example about forgetting it was שבת, Shabbos, you'd still only bring one?
Okay, well let's say you forgot it was אסור assur to eat
חמץ. chametz. I say it's let's say you forgot it was אסור
assur to eat חמץ. chametz. You're saying it's not three separate things.
I'm saying if you
did because that case of שבת Shabbos altogether, that would be more
parallel to the פסח Pesach where you forgot it was פסח. Pesach.
I see you're saying so you're saying that it was I understand
your question, that it's not a good analogy because they're not three
separate things you forgot. Okay, so I'll give you another example.
Let's say but the תורה Torah says don't do מלאכה, melacha, right?
Right, the תורה Torah says right, it only calls it one thing.
We have divided it into thirty-nine, but we've only forgotten one thing
of doing מלאכה. melacha. Meaning why right, the way to phrase it
is here's the way to phrase it. Let's say I didn't forget
it was פסח. Pesach. Let's say I forgot you're not allowed to
eat חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, right? So since the תורה Torah
only says one לאו lav of don't eat חמץ, chametz, even though
I ate three different types of חמץ, chametz, I only it was
only one לאו lav I forgot and I only and therefore it's
one קרבן. korban. So here, as Dov correctly points out, the תורה
Torah says don't do מלאכה. melacha. So if I forgot that this
constitutes מלאכה melacha and that constitutes מלאכה melacha and that constitutes מלאכה,
melacha, why isn't that just making one, the mistake about that one
prohibition in the תורה? Torah? Why is it seen as three separate
acts? Okay, so yes.
Wouldn't it depend on whether or not you consider הבערה havarah ללאו
יצאה? lelav yatza?
Oh, we're getting there. Yeah. Okay, Paula?
Is this not the question they're asking, is how do we know?
Yes, that's the question. How do we conceptualize different מלאכות melachos as
not just generic חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and like do you want
to know if what you did was a חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos,
we got a long list of things that are חילול שבת chilul
Shabbos and they're all one big category of חילול שבת? chilul Shabbos?
How do you know to define them as separate ways as conceptually
right, separate types of חילול שבת? chilul Shabbos? That is the question.
Wait, Paula's still up, yeah.
One more question.
It seems like if we really died or were punishable by death
for violating שבת, Shabbos, we wouldn't be here now.
Well, it's only well, that's a separate issue. No, well that's a
separate issue that the גמרא, Gemara, although the תורה Torah seems like
you would be killing people left and right for various things, the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, defines that it's only in extremely narrow circumstances
which basically never happened that you could actually prosecute somebody. So that's
like a discussion in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, but the basic answer is no.
Yes. How was that phrased? That then you have to explain it
every time. All right, the גמרא's Gemara not going to stick with
it. Let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like this: ומאי
יומת, u'mai yumas, what does it mean יומת? yumat? If we're talking
about שוגג, shogeg, יומת בממון yumat bemamon means it's going to cost
you money, you're going to have to bring another קרבן. korban. Very
funny phrase, יומת בממון. yumat bemamon. Anyway, okay, so that's what שמואל
Shmuel says. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara has a presumably a lot
better answers and it asks why שמואל Shmuel had to go there.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, ותיפוק ליה
חילוק מלאכות מהיכא דנפקא ליה לרבי נתן? v'teipokei chiluk melachos meheicha d'nafka
lei l'Rabbi Noson?
Why didn't שמואל Shmuel learn it out from where רבי נתן Rabbi
Noson learned it out? Where did רבי נתן Rabbi Noson learn it
out? דתניא, Detanya, it was taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי נתן
אומר, Rabbi Noson omer, לא תבערו אש בכל מושבותיכם ביום השבת. lo
siva'aru eish bechol moshvoseichem beyom haShabbos. You shall not make a fire
in all of your dwelling places on שבת. Shabbos.
That is the one specific act that the תורה Torah identifies that
is prohibited on
שבת. Shabbos. Or implicitly it also says that somehow מקושש עצים mekoshish
etzim was prohibited on שבת, Shabbos, whatever that was. Okay, but anyway
that this is the one explicit prohibition the תורה Torah articulates. So
מה תלמוד לומר, Mah talmud lomar, what's the point of saying that?
לפי שנאמר ויקהל משה את כל עדת בני ישראל, Lefi shenemar Vayakhel
Moshe es kol adas bnei Yisrael, משה Moshe gathers the children of
ישראל. Israel. אלה הדברים, Eileh hadvarim,
these are the things that God commanded לעשות אתם ששת ימים תעשה
מלאכה וביום la'asos osam, sheishes yamim ta'aseh melachah u'vayom
and then it says six days to work on the seventh day
rest. ששת ימים תעשה מלאכה, Sheishes yamim ta'aseh melachah, so דברים הדברים
אלה הדברים. dvarim, hadvarim, eileh hadvarim.
It says these are the things
and that's a preface to the prohibitions of שבת, Shabbos, and this
is in the beginning of ויקהל, Vayakhel, and it could have said
דברים. dvarim. Why does it say extra things? אלה Eileh and הדברים.
hadvarim.
So the דרשה drasha we're going to make is the following: the
גימטריא gematria of אלה eileh is what? 36.
36. So and because דברים dvarim and הדברים hadvarim basically, right, the
גימטריא gematria is, let me just check רש"י. Rashi. I think it's
basically because דברים dvarim is plural and the ה heh adds extra
one. Yeah, דברים dvarim is plural and ה heh is one, so
you get three plus 36, somehow you get 39 from אלה הדברים.
eileh hadvarim. I will remind you that when we did this earlier
in the גמרא, Gemara, the very beautiful article that Rav Yoel Bin-Nun
had about it, where he said that it's not about גימטריא gematria
at all. He says that afterwards when the תורה Torah lists in
ויקהל Vayakhel all of the different items of the משכן Mishkan
and it lists it again like in פקודי, Pikudei, if you count
them in both lists you have exactly 39 items. So he says
the דרשה drasha actually is that the תורה Torah is telling you
these are the things, you know, that are building the משכן Mishkan
and you're not allowed to do on שבת, Shabbos, and 39 different
things tells us 39 categories. That's the way he understood it. But
anyway let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So it says,
anyway but we already know 39 מלאכות. melachos. אלה שלשים ותשע מלאכות
שנאמרו למשה בסיני. Eileh shloshim v'tisha melachos shene'emru l'Moshe b'Sinai. 39 מלאכות
melachos that were given to משה Moshe at סיני. Sinai. So we
already know there's 39 מלאכות melachos and presumably we already know that
fire is one of them. Why did the תורה Torah have to
make a special prohibition by fire?
יכול כשעשאן כלם בהעלם אחד אינו חייב אלא אחת, Yachol k'she'asam kulam
b'he'elam echad eino chayav ela achas, that maybe if you did all
of them in one state of forgetfulness, right, you did all 39,
maybe it's only one קרבן. korban. תלמוד לומר בחריש ובקציר תשבת. Talmud
lomar: b'charish u'v'katzir tishbos. There's another place that the תורה Torah actually
identifies things we're not allowed to do and in the positive language
in שמות, Shemos, in you know earlier in שמות, Shemos, in משפטים,
Mishpatim, it says you shall rest on חריש charish and קציר, katzir,
plowing and harvesting. So there we also have things that are mentioned
specifically and maybe the fact that the תורה Torah identifies specifically different
things, it doesn't just genericize it as מלאכה, melachah, it says gives
it a different identity: חריש charish and קציר. katzir. Maybe that tells
us that each one is a separate קרבן. korban. Okay, that should
tell us the idea of separate קרבנות. korbanos. But no, ועדין אני
אומר, v'adayin ani omer, I could still have argued: אחרישה ואקצירה חייב
שתים, Acharisha v'alkatzira chayav shtayim, fine for those two you have to
bring separate קרבנות korbanos because they have been identified specifically and given
different labels. For those two you bring separate קרבנות. korbanos. ועל כלן,
V'al kulan, on all of the rest, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino
chayav ela achas. Maybe it's only one קרבן, korban, the rest remains
generic. How do I know to treat it as 39 separate categories
for קרבנות? korbanos? So maybe I would say that. תלמוד לומר לא
תבערו אש. Talmud lomar: lo teva'aru esh. Therefore you have the פסוק
pasuk specifically about fire. הבערה בכלל היתה, Hav'ara b'chlal hayta, fire was
included in מלאכה, melachah, it was in the big generic category. ולמה
יצאת, V'lamah yatza'at, why was it taken out of the generic category?
להקיש ולהשיב Lehakesh u'lehashiv so that you could connect things to it,
you should use it as a
paradigm and tell
you מה הבערה שהיא אב מלאכה? Mah hav'ara she'hi av melachah? Number
one is it's a chief category, it's an אב מלאכה, av melachah,
it's one of the chief 39 categories because we already know from
אלה הדברים eileh hadvarim that there are 39 categories. What we don't
know is that there are 39 separate קרבן. korban. This is the
stages the גמרא Gemara is working. First we have this idea דברים
הדברים אלה הדברים, dvarim, hadvarim, eileh hadvarim, there are 39 categories. Fine,
39 categories, that tells me what I can't do. But maybe at
the end of the day it's all one prohibition and it would
all be one קרבן korban no matter how many violations. So now
we're going to say ah, but fire is singled out from those
39. And what do I know is true about fire? Number one
is that it's an אב מלאכה, av melachah, it's one of those
39. And number two, וחייבין עליה בפני עצמה, v'chayavin aleha bifne atzma,
and that you are get a separate, you know,
prohibition for it, that fire is singled out to tell you it's
an אב מלאכה av melachah and it's treated separately which presumably means
you bring a separate קרבן. korban. If that's true about fire, I'll
say, אף כל שהוא אב מלאכה חייבין עליו בפני עצמו. af kol
she'hu av melachah chayavin alav bifne atzmo. Anything therefore that is an
אב מלאכה av melachah is a separate, is one of the 39,
you have a separate liability for a separate קרבן. korban. So how
we're saying this idea works in two stages. First where do we
get the number 39 from? You might remember an earlier גמרא Gemara
that said it says 39 times מלאכה melachah in the תורה Torah
and we had to figure out how that worked. But anyway we
have some knowledge of 39: דברים ה dvarim, ha אלה הדברים. Eleh
Hadvarim. Good, we know there's thirty-nine categories. Next question is, how do
I know that if I violate multiple categories I see those as
separate sort of separate types of sins and separate קרבנות? korbanot? Maybe
it's all just one קרבן korban even though there are thirty-nine things
that are forbidden. And that we learn out from the fact that
fire was singled out. Fire was one of those categories, it was
taken out and held up and said, don't do fire. I already
know I'm not supposed to. Ah, it's to tell me, treat it
separately, and treat each one of the thirty-nine separately, and therefore each
one is a separate קרבן. korban. This is the general principle of
דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד, davar shehayah baklal v'yatza min
haklal lilamed, something that was part of a category and it was
taken out of the category and a particular law was set about
it, לא ללמד על עצמו יצא, lo lilamed al atzmo yatza, it
wasn't to tell you just that this is something about this one
member of the group, אלא ללמד על הכלל כולו יצא, ela lilamed
al haklal kulo yatza,
it's to tell you that this is true about all members of
the group. So if fire is treated separately, all thirty-nine are treated
separately. Now, there's an obvious question, which is, why couldn't you have
done that a minute ago with the חריש והקציר? charish v'hakatzir? Why
did you have to wait till you said, well, that's true by
חריש וקציר, charish v'katzir, maybe it's not true about the rest? So
why is fire any better? So רש״י Rashi says, because חריש וקציר
charish v'katzir are not prohibited with a לאו, lav, they're prohibited with
an עשה, aseh, right? ובחריש ובקציר תשבות. uv'charish uv'katzir tishbot.
So you can't use that as an example that they're treated as
a separate prohibition. They just have a separate positive מצוה. mitzvah. Fine,
but that doesn't tell you separate קרבנות. korbanot. We're trying to learn
separate קרבנות. korbanot. The other thing רש״י Rashi said is that it's
two and there's a general rule that you don't learn from two
things, you learn from one thing, but if it's two things, שני
כתובים, shnei ketuvim, then maybe they are an exception and rather than
the rule. That's what רש״י Rashi says. I do want to also
say another point, תוספות Tosafot likes the second answer. Another point which
תוספות Tosafot brings in, which is that, which also answers this question
of חריש וקציר. charish v'katzir. And he brings it in from the
מכילתא. Mechilta. It's not exactly our גירסא girsa from the גמרא, Gemara,
but he actually thinks that it would be maybe to amend the
גמרא Gemara based on this. The מכילתא Mechilta says, before you ask
the question of do I have to do I bring a separate
קרבן korban for each one of the thirty-nine, the מכילתא Mechilta has
a prior question. Maybe I'm not considered to have violated שבת Shabbat
until I do all thirty-nine? Right? Maybe I have to completely undermine
שבת. Shabbat. Okay, yes, exactly! So that is we learn out from
חריש והקציר charish v'hakatzir that no, no, no, even if you only
violate one or two of them, you've already violated שבת. Shabbat. You
don't have to violate all thirty-nine. Now that I know that I've
already violated שבת, Shabbat, I have a question which if I do
do more than one, how do I know you bring separate קרבנות?
korbanot? And then we learn that out from fire. So that explains
the two stages, there's really three stages, if you would. First we
have to learn the thirty-nine categories of מלאכה. melacha. Then we have
to ask when are you considered to have violated? Maybe it's only
all thirty-nine? No, חריש וקציר charish v'katzir even one of the thirty-nine
you violate. Okay, what if I violate from different categories, is it
one קרבן korban or multiple קרבנות? korbanot? That we learn out from
fire that it is multiple קרבנות, korbanot, each category is considered distinct.
Yes.
You also learn it out from the fact that there's actually a
גימטריא gematria אלה eleh whatever it is. Yeah, don't we also have
another saying that גימטריאות פרפראות לחכמה? gematriot parparaot lachochmah? How are you
learning out an actual הלכה? halacha?
Every now and then you do learn it out, and anyway here
the גמרא Gemara also uses the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai, נאמר למשה
מסיני. ne'emar l'Moshe m'Sinai. So could it be that we started with
that tradition and we worked backwards? But sometimes you learn certain things
out from actually it wasn't from a, yeah, sometimes you do learn
out from a גמרא. Gemara. An actual הלכה? halacha? Yeah, I mean
like we'll learn out סתם נזירות שלשים יום stam nezirut shloshim yom
according to one is learned out because קדוש יהיה, kadosh yihyeh, יהיה
yihyeh by גימטריא שלשים, gematria shloshim, so it's not unheard of. Okay,
so basically saying פרפראות לחכמה
parparaot lachochmah isn't necessarily true.
Most of the time. Okay, let's let's keep on going. The גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So why did שמואל Shmuel not learn it out from that? That's
a great דרשה. drasha. So the גמרא Gemara says שמואל סבר לה
כרבי יוסי, Shmuel savar lah k'Rabbi Yossi, שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. דאמר הבערה ללאו יצאת, d'amar havarah l'lav yatzat,
because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says fire is not coming to tell
you a rule about the whole category that each one is treated
separately, it's actually coming to downgrade fire, that fire is not prohibited
by death and כרת, karet, fire on שבת Shabbat is just a
simple negative prohibition. The same way according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
going outside the boundaries of the city is prohibited on שבת, Shabbat,
or having your animal work is prohibited on שבת, Shabbat, but it's
not one of the מלאכות melachot that you're punishable by death. Fire
also is a simple לאו lav according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
which is shocking. דתניא, D'tanya, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, הבערה ללאו יצאת
דברי רבי יוסי. havarah l'lav yatzat divrei Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi says fire was came out of the category to teach you
that it's a simple לאו. lav. רבי נתן אומר לחלק יצאת. Rabbi
Natan omer l'chalek yatzat. No, it's coming to divide, to tell you
that each one of the categories of the מלאכות melachot is considered
separate and therefore a separate קרבן. korban. So if שמואל Shmuel holds
like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, therefore he could not learn it out
from the use of from fire. Okay, ותיפוק ליה דחילוק מלאכות מהיכא
דנפקא ליה לרבי יוסי. v'teipok lei d'chiluk melachot meiheicha d'nafka lei l'Rabbi
Yossi. Fine, you don't want to learn it out from fire, but
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi also couldn't learn it out from fire and
he has a different place where he learns out thirty-nine מלאכות. melachot.
And why are you running to your פסוק? pasuk? Where did רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi learn it out from? דתניא *Detanya*, we taught in
the ברייתא *baraisa*. רבי יוסי אומר *Rebbi Yosi omer*, ועשה מאחת מהנה
*V'asah me'achas meihena*. It says that this is in the in the
place in ויקרא *Vayikra* where it says where it talks about the
חטאת chatas. *chatas*. And somebody who sins and does violates one of
the מצות *mitzvos*, ועשה *v'asah* and he does מאחת מהנה *me'achas meihena*
from one of the מצות *mitzvos* then you bring a קרבן korban
חטאת chatas *korban chatas*. So let's see what the דרשה drasha, *drasha*
is. So this is a focus on פסוקים *pesukim* about חטאת chatas
*chatas*, not a focus on פסוקים *pesukim* about about about שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos*, but we're going to let's see what we do with it.
פעמים שחייבים אחת achat על כולן ופעמים שחייבים על כל אחת achat
ואחת *Pe'amim she'chayavim achas al kulan u'pe'amim she'chayavim al kol achas v'achas*.
So there's אחת *achas*, there's one, and there's מהנה *meihena*. מהנה *Meihena*
is them, they, multiple. So sometimes you bring only one קרבן korban
*korban*, אחת *achas*, and sometimes you bring, you know, מהנה *meihena*, you
bring for multiple violations. Even though, but of course this is being
read through the lens of שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. You can bring multiple
קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos* for for one שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. How? For having
done separate מלאכות melachot *melachos*. So that's the אחת *achas* tells you
there are times like if you forgot it was שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*,
you'll bring one, there are times מהנה *meihena* that you will bring
multiple. Okay,
one minute we are go we are going we are not done
with the דרשה drasha. *drasha*. Let's take a look. Okay, ואמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא *V'amar Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi Chanina*, מאי טעמא דרבי
יוסי *Mai ta'ama d'Rebbi Yosi*? So said רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Rebbi
Yosi b'Rebbi Chanina*, what is the reasoning of רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yosi*,
meaning let's spell this out a little more exactly what the דרשה
drasha *drasha* is. So אחת *achas* מאחת *me'achas*. It could have said
one and it says מאחת *me'achas*, from one. מהנה *meihena*. It could
have said they, from them, מהנה *meihena* and it says from them.
Of course we you would tell me that the grammar it had
to say אחת מהנה *achas meihena*, fine, I don't care. Anyway, אחת
*achas*, so here are the דרשות drashot. *drashos*. We're going to make
a דרשה *drasha* from the juxtaposition of אחת *achas* and הנה heina,
*henna*, one of them, and we're going to make דרשות *drashos* from
the extra from what's considered to be the extra מ'ס *mems*. Let's
see all the דרשות *drashos* that we learn out. Okay. אחת שהיא
הנה, heina, הנה שהיא אחת *Achas she'hi henna, henna she'hi achas*. You
can have one violation that is multiple and multiple that is one,
meaning what? You can forget it is שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* and therefore
violate multiple times, but in the end it started with a core
of one, אחת *achas*, which led to הנה *henna*, led to multiple
violations, but it started with one thing, you forgot it was שבת
Shabbat. *Shabbos*, so one קרבן korban *korban*. You could also have הנה
*henna* multiple which is one, which is basically you do multiple מלאכות
melachot *melachos*, one in the sense that it happened on one שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos*, but anyway it's multiple and therefore you would bring multiple
חטאות *chataos*. Okay, so therefore you can have a case of one
חטאת *chatas*, you can have a case of multiple חטאות *chataos*. Then
we also say, אחת שהיא הנה, הנה שהיא אחת *achas she'hi henna,
henna she'hi achas*. Okay, so that's that. אחת *achas* שמעון Shimon *Shimon*.
Now we're going to focus on the מ' *mem*. So it says
one would be you wrote the name שמעון *Shimon*. מאחת *Me'achas*, from
one, means you didn't even do the whole thing you were intending.
שם משמעון Shem mi'Shimon, *Shem m'Shimon*. You were writing the word שמעון
*Shimon* and you stopped at שם *Shem*. Okay, now שם *shem* is
also a word. It's a little funny because it's a מ' *mem*
not a מ' סופית *mem sofis*, but okay. But you did exactly
what you intended, you intended to write ש' מ' *shin mem* and
you wrote ש' מ' *shin mem*, except you didn't finish what you
intended, you intended to write the full name שמעון *Shimon*, you stopped
after two letters, but you know what? You're also חייב chayav *chayav*
because writing two letters on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* is a מלאכה melacha,
*melacha* and you did what you intended even though you didn't complete
what you intended, and therefore that's מאחת *me'achas*, even if you only
did a portion of the larger thing you were trying to do.
That's what we learn from the מ' *mem* from מאחת *me'achas*. מהנה
*Meihena*. Now what do we learn from the מ' *mem* מהנה *meihena*?
From those. So הנה *henna* is אבות *avos*. The idea that there
are major categories, thirty-nine, you know, fathers of מלאכה melacha, *melacha*. מהנה
*Meihena*, from those, means תולדות *toldos*, means descendants. Okay, so from the
אחת הנה achat heina *achas henna* juxtaposition, we're saying that sometimes it's
funny, again this whole פסוקים *pesukim* isn't talking about שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*,
it's talking about a חטאת *chatas*, but we're reading it through the
lens of שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos*. Okay, so therefore the אחת הנה achat
heina. *achas henna* juxtaposition, one and many, that there's ways you could
bring one קרבן korban. *korban* on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, ways you could
bring many קרבנות korbanot. *korbanos* on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. The מאחת *me'achas*
tells you even if you do partially what you intended it could
be a violation, and מהנה *meihena* tells you there's something that derives
from the multiplicity, there derives from the אבות מלאכה melacha. *avos melacha*
are the תולדות *toldos*. And now we're just going to finish spelling
it out. אחת שהיא הנה *Achas she'hi henna*, one which is many,
זדון שבת Shabbat ושגגת מלאכות melachot, *zedon Shabbos v'shigegas melachos*. I might
have said it accidentally reversed before, okay, but anyway it is you
know it is שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and you make a mistake about
the מלאכות melachot. *melachos*, so it is one thing which is many
because it is many different forgetting, many different מלאכות melachot. *melachos*, so
therefore you bring multiple קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*. הנה שהיא אחת *Henna she'hi
achas*, many which are one, שגגת שבת Shabbat וזדון *shigegas Shabbos v'zedon*
So one which is many is where it was one שבת Shabbat
but it was many different violations because many different forgettings, you forgot
each מלאכה, Melachah, you bring multiple, and many which is one is
yes you did multiple things but at the end of the day
you only bring one קרבן Korban. because it was only one mistake
of forgetting that it was שבת. Shabbat, Okay, now, and then we'd
just repeat what we said. ושמואל אחת, V'Shmuel achat, שמואל Shmuel is
one, I'm sorry did I say? ושמואל אחת? V'Shmuel achat? Right, go
ahead, hold on, hold on. ושמואל אחת, V'Shmuel achat, right. So שמואל,
Shmuel, and so שמואל Shmuel why did, because I have the שם
משמעון, but that was שמעון not שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, ושמואל, V'Shmuel, why
did שמואל Shmuel not learn it from that? That's a great דרשה,
אחת מאחת, achat mei'achat, אחת הנה achat heina and the whole thing.
אחת שהיא הנה והנה שהיא אחת לא משמע ליה. Achat sheheina v'heina
she'achat lo mashma lei. He's not so persuaded by that דרשה. Very
nice, you combine two words, אחת and הנה, I don't see where
you get מלאכות melachot, from that. Okay, but now we have three
derivations of the idea of חילוק מלאכות. chiluk melachot. Two Tannaitic and
one which is שמואל, Shmuel, which is interesting, it's Amoraic. So תוספות
Tosafos wants to know why did he argue on תנאים? Tannaim? Maybe
he had some מסורה. mesorah. Anyway, the two Tannaitic are fire, fire
is taken out and singled out to tell you each one is
separate. This juxtaposition of אחת and הנה, one and many. Sometimes you
could do many מלאכות Melachos, and bring one קרבן Korban. or sometimes
it could be one שבת Shabbat. and you bring many קרבנות, korbanot
and that's to tell you that if you forget about the מלאכות,
Melachos, you bring multiple קרבנות. korbanot, So that's אחת הנה. שמואל Shmuel
doesn't like either of those דרשות. He thinks fire is a לאו,
lav, אחת הנה he doesn't buy that that juxtaposition is telling you
that. And he has a דרשה which seems to be the weakest
actually, which is יומת, yumat, the double language of מיתה mita means
that you could see it as multiple different עבירות aveirot for different
מלאכות. Melachos, Oh, good, yes. See we say שמי משמואל, Shemi mishmuel,
to me it sounds like, I don't know if that's like the
best example because I don't, that's not actually a word. Yeah, yeah,
I don't want to deal with it, we'll deal with it, I
don't want to deal with it, we'll deal with it when we
deal with כתיבה. ksiva. Okay. בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. Bayei minei
Rava meiRav Nachman. רבא Rava asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. העלם זה
וזה בידו מהו? He'lem zeh v'zeh biyado mahu? Now we're going to
see where the answer in the גמרא, Gemara, remember we had two
answers before, is it what would have stopped you from doing or
is it what you made your mistake in, maybe there'll be a
נפקא מינה nafka mina between those. Let's say you forgot both. I
both forgot it was שבת Shabbat, and even if you would have
reminded me it was שבת Shabbat. or I would have remembered it
was שבת, Shabbat? I would have gone on watering my plants because
I forgot you're not allowed to water your plants on שבת. Shabbat
So I thought it's Wednesday and I'm watering my plants, okay, but
even if I had known it was שבת Shabbat I would have
because I forgot you're not allowed to do that on שבת. Shabbat.
And not only did I water my plants thinking it was Wednesday,
I also you know I also baked thinking it was Wednesday and
I never knew you weren't allowed to bake on שבת. Shabbos, Okay,
so how many קרבנות Korbanos, do I bring? Do I bring two
קרבנות Korbanos because I forgot you can't water your plants and you
forgot you can't bake? Or do I bring one קרבן Korban. because
I thought it was Wednesday and I forgot it was שבת? Shabbos.
Okay, so. בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. Bayei minei Rava meiRav Nachman.
רבא Rava asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. העלם זה וזה בידו מהו?
He'lem zeh v'zeh biyado mahu? Let's say you forgot both of them.
Both שבת Shabbos, and that these were מלאכות. Melachos, אמר ליה, Amar
lei, הרי העלם שבת בידו. harei he'lem Shabbat biyado. Look, you forgot
it was שבת. Shabbos, That would have led to all the other
things anyway. So therefore it all hinges on the שבת Shabbos, and
it's only one. We're being nice on you, you don't have to
bring two קרבנות, Korbanos? you bring one because at the end of
the day that mistake would have led to all of these actions
anyway. ואינו חייב אלא אחת, V'eino chayav ela achat, you only bring
one. אדרבה, Adderaba, say the opposite, הרי העלם מלאכות בידו וחייב על
כל אחת ואחת. harei he'lem melachot biyado v'chayav al kol achat v'achat.
Say the opposite, that you forgot the מלאכות, Melachos. those were separate
things and therefore those should be considered as and had even had
you known it was שבת Shabbos those mistakes would have led to
it. So therefore that should be you know you should be bringing
a separate קרבן. Korban, You do understand the logic, not just maybe
a desire to be lenient which תוספות Tosafos also discusses maybe there's
a push for a particular reason to be lenient here, but anyway,
you do understand the logic, right? שבת Shabbos is the bigger mistake.
It's the one that includes the other mistakes. The other mistakes like
each individual mistake about watering your plants and baking do not imply
the other things. But שבת Shabbos implies everything else. So that's his
position. But the גמרא Gemara isn't satisfied. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela
amar Rav Ashi, said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, חזינן, chazinan, we see,
אם משום שבת קפריש, im mishum Shabbat kaparish, if now this is
again echoing the language we had on the עמוד א, amud aleph,
if you would have stopped doing it because of שבת, Shabbos. הרי
העלם שבת בידו, harei he'lem Shabbat biyado, then it's really about forgetting
it was שבת. Shabbos, ואינו חייב אלא אחת, V'eino chayav ela achat,
and it's only one. ואם משום מלאכה קפריש, Ve'im mishum melacha kaparish,
if you had stopped doing it because you knew it was a
מלאכה, melachah הרי העלם מלאכות בידו, harei he'lem melachot biyado, then it's
fundamentally about forgetting it's a מלאכה. melachah, וחייב על כל אחת ואחת,
V'chayav al kol achat v'achat, you're חייב chayav each one. Now of
course the obvious point is like if you knew it was שבת,
Shabbos, you still thought that you're allowed to water your plants on
שבת. Shabbos So what does he mean that you would have stopped
because you had known it was שבת? Shabbos. רש"י Rashi says what
it means if somebody said stop it's שבת Shabbos, or whatever, you
know if somebody just said it's שבת Shabbos? you would have said
then that thing is שבת. Shabbos? would have made you realize A,
it's שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and B, why's he yelling at me? It
must be I'm not allowed to water water my plants on שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos*. Okay, but if somebody was to come and say to
me, "You can't water your plants on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*," and I'm
thinking it's Wednesday, but maybe maybe he's just giving me a little
שיעור *shiur* to tell, you know, but but if I would have
realized, "Oh, wait, he's telling me that, it must be that today
is שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*," okay, then mentioning one, if mentioning one would
have suggested the other to me, then it is then that one
is the key. So תוספות *Tosafos* basically says, "I don't get why
that matters. At the end of the day, you forgot both and
who cares what sort of, you know, how you would have inferred
one from the other and anyway, even if I said it's שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos* and you were to stop, doesn't mean had I done
the reverse it wouldn't have also had the equal effect, right?" So
תוספות *Tosafos* doesn't like רש"י *Rashi's* answer. So תוספות *Tosafos's* answer about
focusing in one rather than the other, let me just just re-read
it quickly to make sure that it's correctly, is one minute. Right,
is that not what somebody would have told me and what I
would have inferred, but that we ask me to sort of hypothesize
and say, "Look, had you remembered it's שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, right, would
you still have gone ahead and watered your plants?" you know, and
you could say, "Look, it's true that I, you know, I'm pretty
much I'm sure that you're allowed to water your plants on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat*, but had I had I known it was שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat*, I probably would have hesitated or asked or clarified that issue
or whatever." So you yourself are self-reporting, it's not what you would
have figured out why is this guy yelling at me? But we
ask you, had you known one of those facts, would you have
stopped, would that have been enough for you to not have done
it? Because maybe having known one of those would have made you
hesitate and double check about the other point. And if you tell
us that having known one would have made you hesitate about the
other, and that the real thing I forgot was the fact that
it was שבת Shabbos? *Shabbat*, the watering I vaguely maybe thought maybe
yes, maybe no, but the real thing I forgot was שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat*, or the reverse. The real thing I forgot was the watering.
I was a little ambivalent about whether it was really שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbat* or I thought Wednesday, but I might have been mistaken. So
you knew that one was more key and the other one you
only sort of forgot, then we'd go with the one that was
more key. That's the way תוספות *Tosafos* reads it. It's about like
a- it's about a self-reporting. Right. And then תוספות *Tosafos* says, "So
one minute, that doesn't answer our key question, because let's say you
really didn't know both." So it says, "Okay, but we're trying to
narrow the field. Maybe if you can tell us one was more
fundamental forgetting, maybe at least that's the one we would focus on."
So that's the way תוספות *Tosafos* reasons. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara's* response- גמרא Gemara *Gemara* response to this. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *Amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi*
so רבינא *Ravina* said back to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, "One minute,
again, כלום פרש משבת אלא משום מלאכות Melachos, *klum parash mi-Shabbos ela
mishum melachos*? Exactly the phrase used on the עמוד א Amud Aleph,
*Amud Aleph* with the with the, you know, explaining the משנה *Mishna*.
The reason if I say, 'Hey, it's שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*,' the reason
you stop is because you also realize that it's a מלאכה melachah,
*melacha*. כלום פירש ממלאכות אלא משום שבת Shabbos mistake. *Klum piresh mi-melachos
ela mishum Shabbos*? And if I say, 'You can't water your plants
on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*,' then the reason you're stopping is not only
that you remembered it's a
מלאכה melacha *melacha*, but
also you added to it that you remembered it's שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*.
So at the end of the day, you need to know both
points. And if you've forgotten both points, then I still don't have
my answer to my question. According to תוספות *Tosafos*, the way what
he's really saying is is that you haven't addressed the case when
you really forgot both. Maybe you've addressed the case where you fundamentally
forget one and are ambivalent about the other, but you haven't really
addressed the case when you really forgot both. Okay, according to רש"י
*Rashi*, the point is just the obvious point. If I yell at
you, 'It's שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*,' then you figure out the other one,
but at the- but at the end of the day, it's you
had forgotten at the moment you had forgotten both." So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara's* still not happy. If you forgot both, you forgot both.
How are you telling me which one is key? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא לא שנא *Ela lo shena*. So at least
רבינא *Ravina* says, it doesn't matter whether you- you know, which one
would have made you stop, it's all the same, all the same
which way. So as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will make clear, it's
all the same going back to the first point, that it's only
one. That at the end of the day, שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* is
the bigger mistake. It inf- it suggests all the rest, you know,
it would have made you do everything else. And therefore, if you
have both, you go by the bigger category, you go by שבת
Shabbat, *Shabbat*. That's רבינא *Ravina's* point. So although the גמרא *Gemara's* trying
to say maybe under certain circumstances the מלאכות Melachos? *melachos* are עיקר
*ikkar*, רבינא *Ravina* saying no, it doesn't matter, it's all about שבת
Shabbat. *Shabbat*. Okay. תנן *Tenan*. Now we're going to see if we
can prove this one way or the other. אבות מלאכות Melachos, ארבעים
חסר אחת *Avos melachos arba'im chaser achas*. Back to, there's a nice
symmetry about the גמרא *Gemara* we're doing today, the עמוד א Amud
Aleph, *Amud Aleph* and the עמוד ב *Amud Beis*. So there are
thirty-nine categories of מלאכות Melachos, *melachos*. והוינן בה *Va-havinan bah*, we asked
about this, מנינא למה לי *minyana lama li*? Why do you need
to tell me thirty-nine? I can count. ואמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan,
*Ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan* שאם עשאן כולם בהעלם אחד *she-im asaan kulam be-helem
echad* חייב chayav על כל אחת ואחת *chayav al kol achas ve-achas*.
To tell you it's possible to bring thirty-nine קרבנות Korbanos *korbanos* on-
for one שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. That you forgot all the categories and
you did every single thing possib- humanly possible, and you're going to
bring thirty-nine קרבנות Korbanos *korbanos*. Okay, now we get to our old
question. If you forgot that you all the מלאכות Melachos, *melachos*, how
did you remember it was שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*? We answered that already,
but this is a different סוגיא *sugya*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: אי אמרת בשלמא העלם זה וזה *Iy amrat bishlama helem
zeh ve-zeh*... אי אמרת בשלמא העלם זה וזה בידך חייב chayav על
כל אחת ואחת, if you say that if you forget all the
מלאכות, Melachos, and which essentially means you forgot שבת, Shabbos, so that's
our case. You forgot the מלאכות, Melachos certain מלאכות, Melachos. we were
talking about two or three, and you forgot it was שבת. Shabbos.
So fine, you forgot both, but if you say that in that
case you still bring for every separate מלאכה, melacha then we can
understand this scenario very easily. You forgot all the מלאכות, melachot which
implicitly means you forgot it was שבת, Shabbat, because you didn't realize
anything was אסור assur to do on שבת, Shabbat. okay, and you
can still bring 39 קרבנות, Korbanos, because even when you forget both,
you still bring for the separate מלאכות. melachot, Then that works. שפיר,
Shapir, it works. אלא אי אמרת העלם שבת בידו, Ella ee amrit
hellem Shabbos b'yado, but if you say once even if you forget
the individual מלאכות, melachot. once you forget that it's שבת, Shabbat it
all focuses on the שבת Shabbat, and it's one קרבן. Korban. אינו
חייב אלא אחת, Eino chayav ela achas, and therefore you only bring
one. היכי משכחת לה? Heichi mishkachat lei? How can you get the
scenario of 39 קרבנות Korbanos. בזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות, b'zadon shabbos v'shiggas
melachos, that you knew it was שבת Shabbat and you made errors
in the מלאכות? melachot. According to you, if you both forgot it
was שבת Shabbos and forgot the מלאכות, melachot. it's basically just forgetting
it was שבת. Shabbos So how does רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan how
do you get the case of רבי יוחנן of bringing 39 קרבנות?
Korbanos, If you forgot all those מלאכות, it's essentially you forgot it
was שבת, Shabbos and according to you when you do both things,
it's only one קרבן. Korban. So the גמרא says הניחא אי סבר
לה כרבי יוחנן hani nicha ee savar lei k'Rabbi Yochanan דאמר כיון
דשגג בכרת אף על פי דמזיד בלאו. d'amar kivan d'shagog b'kares af
al pi d'meizid b'lav. If you recall yesterday's discussion that even though
you know it's forbidden, as long as you didn't realize it was
כרת, kares, that's enough of an error to bring a קרבן. Korban.
So then it's easy. משכחת לה דידע ליה שבת בלאו. Mishkachat lei
d'yadah lei Shabbos b'lav. You knew all 39 things of these categories
were prohibited. You forgot how bad it was. You forgot that they
were punishable by כרת. kares. So you know it's שבת, Shabbat, but
you made a mistake of every single one of those 39 categories
thinking that it wasn't כרת. kares. And therefore you can bring 39
קרבנות Korbanos, and still know it was שבת Shabbat because you knew
at least they were prohibited. But it's a קרבן, Korban you're considered
שוגג shogeg because you forgot how bad it was. אלא אי סבר
לה כריש לקיש, Ella ee savar lei k'Reish Lakish, but if you
hold like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish דאמר עד דישגוג בלאו ובכרת, d'amar
ad d'yishgog b'lav u'bkares, that you have to both forget that not
only that it's punishable by כרת kares but that it's prohibited altogether.
So if you forgot all 39 categories, it meant you forgot that
all 39 of these things were prohibited on שבת. Shabbat, Well then
that equals forgetting it was שבת, Shabbat and then that should become
not 39 קרבנות Korbanos but one קרבן. korban. So how do you
get forgetting all 39 and still bring 39 קרבנות, korbanot not turning
it into a case of forgetting that it was שבת? So the
גמרא says like the גמרא said two days ago, דידע ליה שבת
במאי? d'yadah lei Shabbos b'mai? How do you still know it was
שבת? דידע ליה בתחומין ואליבא דרבי עקיבא. d'yadah lei b'tchumin v'aliba d'Rabbi
Akiva. You know it's שבת because you know at least per רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you're not allowed to go, it's biblical you can't
go outside the city limits. So therefore it's not like you totally
forgot that it was שבת. You remembered it was שבת for some
relevant idea of prohibition. It's not enough to remember let's say that
you make קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה. Havdalah. You have to know that
it's for some relevant category of something is prohibited. You knew תחומין
tchumin was prohibited biblically according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and therefore
you knew it was שבת and you made mistakes of 39 מלאכות,
39 קרבנות. korbanot But if you didn't hold that way and you
made mistakes of all 39 מלאכות, then essentially you think you can
do מלאכה on שבת, which is equivalent to forgetting שבת, forgetting what's
relevant about שבת for קרבנות, korbanot forgetting that שבת is prohibited in
מלאכה, and therefore it's all one mistake and therefore you would only
bring one קרבן. korban, Okay, so that's what the גמרא says when
העלם זה וזה בידו, hellem zeh v'zeh b'yado, you only bring one
קרבן. korban Now I think that this might explain what seemed to
be the somewhat sort of exactly same statement on עמוד א', where
the גמרא first said why do you bring multiple קרבנות, korbanot you
know, for מלאכות versus one קרבן korban for שבת? And the first
answer is well you would in one case you would have stopped.
You know, if you somebody told you it's אסור assur you would
have stopped. And the other said no, no, no, it's not what
would have made you stop, it's where you made what you made
the mistake is in. I think remember that at the עמוד א',
right, that which seemed to be basically the exact same point? So
I think that here you see a little bit of a difference
because if you forgot both, right, both that it was שבת and
that it was a מלאכה, then I could still say you made
a mistake in the מלאכות. And if we focus on where your
mistakes were, you made multiple mistakes. You made a mistake about שבת,
you made a mistake about baking, you made a mistake about watering,
so maybe that leads to the idea that you would bring multiple
קרבנות korbanot, because you made fundamentally multiple mistakes, right? And that was
one approach. But the other approach was what would have like made
you stop doing it, and that's what the גמרא somehow tries to
answer, that maybe in that scenario maybe שבת was the key or
maybe say the other way, what made you stop is you would
have needed to have both components but the key mistake was the
שבת. But I do think that those different things which sounded almost
identical, what would have made you stop and where was your mistake,
could be played out differently when you actually made multiple. Overlapping mistakes
because then it's a different answer to what would have made you
stop doing what you're doing and where were the mistakes that you
made. Okay, so that's just tying in the first thing we said
today. I hope I haven't confused everybody. What רב נחמן Rav Nachman
was saying... don't worry about it. That was like my little שקלא
וטריא. shakla v'tarya. If you didn't understand it, forget it. Let's move
on to the end. Let's continue going. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Now,
if that wasn't, you know, sort of too complicated, let's take a
look at this case. קצר וטחן כגרוגרת. Katzar v'tachan k'gogeret. You harvested
and ground a כגרוגרת k'gogeret worth of... does it say there how
much like a גרוגרת gogeret says? I know, it's like a dried
fig, but it doesn't give you like a volume measurement? Not really.
Okay, whatever it is. It's a dried fig. It's bigger than a
כזית. k'zayit. Okay, and the standard amount of food that is the
minimum size for מלאכות that relate to food on שבת is a
fig. Okay, is a גרוגרת, gogeret, a dried fig. So you harvested
a minimum amount, a גרוגרת's gogeret worth—this is a volume measure—of, you
know, grain and you ground it. בשגגת שבת וזדון מלאכה. B'shiggat Shabbat
v'zadon melacha. And at that stage, you had forgotten it was שבת.
You thought it was Wednesday. וחזר, V'chazar, then you took a nap
and you woke up and you were disoriented, or whatever, and then
you remembered somehow when you wake up, you remembered it was שבת.
וקצר וטחן כגרוגרת. V'katzar v'tachan k'gogeret. You did the whole thing again.
You harvested again and ground again a minimum amount. בזדון שבת ושגגת
מלאכה. B'zadon Shabbat v'shiggat melacha. And this time, you knew it was
שבת, but you forgot that you weren't allowed to do it. Okay,
you are a... you have a... you should probably be seeing a
doctor anyway, but okay. Anyway, ונודע לו על קצירה וטחינה ששגגת שבת
וזדון מלאכה. v'noda lo al k'tzira v'tichna she-shiggat Shabbat v'zadon melacha. And
then, the order you forgot was like A, B. You know what,
let's call it one, two, because one is one mistake of שבת,
and the two is the mistake of the מלאכות, because you made
two mistakes of two מלאכות. So your order of forgetting was, the
first act was a one, you forgot it was שבת. Your second
mistake, without ever having realized that you sinned, you know, you didn't
sort of put two and two together, you didn't realize you sinned,
but you made now the reverse mistake. It was a two mistake.
You remembered it was שבת, but you forgot the separate מלאכות. So
you made... did a one and then a two, and then you
realized your mistakes in the same order. First you realize mistake number
one, "Oh, in this morning, I was... it was שבת, and therefore
I did that, oh my gosh, I shouldn't have done that." And
now you realize you sinned, and therefore you are חייב chayav in
a קרבן. korban. So now you realize mistake number one, and then
you realize mistake number two. "Oh, and this afternoon, it was also
שבת, and I did those things and you're not allowed to do
those things on שבת." Okay, so you made... you did one, two,
and then you... and then you realized in the same order, one
and then two. Who cares which way you realized? We will see.
Okay. Yes. When you're remind- when you realize that the first... that
in the morning it was שבת, but you knew that קצירה k'tzira
was wrong... Right. How did you not automatically realize what you did
in the afternoon? Right. So it must like, yeah, I know, I
know. It's very hard to understand this. Maybe at that stage you
had forgotten what you had done in the afternoon, so you didn't
actually realize that you had sinned. You had to know that you
had sinned. Right. So you have a real like I said, you
need to be seeing a psychiatrist. But okay, so that's what happened.
Okay. So, ונודע לו על קצירה וטחינה ששגגת שבת וזדון מלאכה. v'noda
lo al k'tzira v'tichna she-shiggat Shabbat v'zadon melacha. First you remembered the
number one mistake, which was you did two things but it was
one mistake, you had forgotten it was שבת. וחזר ונודע לו על
קצירה וטחינה שזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכה. v'chazar v'noda lo al k'tzira v'tichna
she-zadon Shabbat v'shiggat melacha. And then it was known to you the
number two mistake, where you knew it was שבת but you had
forgotten those two separate מלאכות. Okay, so you did one, two, and
then you remembered one, two. So, how many קרבנות korbanot. do you
bring? So before we said you had forgotten the מלאכה and the
שבת, does the forgetting of שבת overwhelm? Here, we actually said you
did different acts: a one act, a שבת forgetting, and a מלאכה
forgetting. How many קרבנות korbanot. do you bring? So let's see what
the... what רבא Rava says. קצירה גוררת קצירה וטחינה גוררת טחינה. K'tzira
goreret k'tzira v'tichna goreret tichna. Since you remembered number one first, and
you first became obligated in the שבת קרבן, korban so here we
totally say that the שבת includes the other things. If you're already
bringing a קרבן korban. for forgetting it was שבת, and that קרבן
korban was for acts that related to קצירה k'tzira and טחינה, tichna,
harvesting and grinding, then any other קרבנות related to harvesting and grinding
are implicitly included in this קרבן. korban Because this קרבן korban. has
already been obligated and it includes grinding and טחינה tichna and therefore
any other קרבנות that would come later would already you'd be, you
know, fit into the first קרבן. korban Does that somewhat clear the
idea? All right. Now you'll see... you'll see by contrasting it to
the other case. אבל נודע לו על קצירה שזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכה.
Aval noda lo al k'tzira she-zadon Shabbat v'shiggat melacha. But let's say
you remembered the reverse. First you remembered the two, and then you
remembered the one. קצירה גוררת קצירה וטחינה שעמו... K'tzira goreret k'tzira v'tichna
she-imo... So here's what you did. You did one and then the
two. This is what you did and then this is what you
remembered. Okay? I don't have to write out what one and two
is, you understand, right? Okay. And then you remembered one and two.
So as soon as you remembered one, you're חייב in a חטאת.
Let's draw a sheep here. Okay. You're חייב in a חטאת and
this little חטאת is being brought because of your שבת משגגת. Shabbat
mish'gagat. But your שבת משגגת, Shabbat mish'gagat, what did you do during
your שבת משגגת? Shabbat mish'gagat? You did קצירה ktsira and טחינה. techina.
Okay. So that's your חיוב. chiyuv. Now you remember two. Two should
have led you to two קרבנות, right? One קרבן korban. for קצירה
ktsira and one קרבן korban, for טחינה. techina. Okay. It should have
led you to those two קרבנות. But you already are חייב in
this and this is already about קצירה ktsira and טחינה, techina, so
you don't have to bring any extra קרבן. korban It's all already
implicitly, you know, included in that. That is scenario number one. But
if you remembered in the reverse order, if you remembered in the
two and the one order, so as soon as you remembered about
two, that leads to a חיוב chiyuv about two קרבנות. Your קצירה
ktsira קרבן korban, and your טחינה techina קרבן. korban. Okay. Now you
said this. This should obligate you in one big whatever שבת קרבן,
korban. okay, which has קצירה ktsira and טחינה. techina. Okay. But what
the case is is that actually you did not remember here, excuse
me, you did not remember here about both things you did. You
only remembered about the קצירה. ktsira. Okay. You only remembered about the
קצירה. ktsira. Then you remembered this. Okay. So what is the story?
The story is is that this, remembering about this, wait, did I
get this right? Hold on one second. אבל נודע לו הקצירה של
זדון, Avel noda lo haktsira shel zadon, right, I got it right.
Okay. אבל נודע לו הקצירה, Avel noda lo haktsira, you only remembered
the קצירה. ktsira. So this, when you remembered this, I don't have
to bring this. Why do I not have to bring this? Because
at least part of this animal, this part of the animal, is
already included. That's קצירה גוררת קצירה. ktsira goreret ktsira. Since you're obligated
in the קצירה ktsira קרבן korban. and this קרבן, korban. a piece
of it is about קצירה, ktsira, you don't have to bring this
קרבן. korban It already is included there. Okay. Now you after that
you remembered your other thing. You remembered your טחינה techina thing. You
have to bring this קרבן. korban Is that clear? This is the
order you remembered. Here you remembered קצירה, ktsira, the whole so you
remembered this, this was somewhat included in that, you don't have to
bring it. But this isn't included in that, so you would have
to bring this קרבן. korban, That makes sense, okay? Really? Right? I
mean for me at some point you're remembering שבת, שבת is the
bigger law. No, but we're not talking about now what you remembered.
We're talking about how your obligations, the remembering leads to a חיוב
chiyuv of a קרבן. korban And the question is an overlapping obligation
you will not have to bring. If it's already included in the
prior obligation. Okay. You've done the sins, you've remembered everything. But at
the moment of remembering it leads to an obligation of a קרבן
and then when you become obligated again, we will not obligate you
again about something that you've already been obligated in. So the understand
let's see this. So here when you remember, since you've partly been
obligated in part of what this is about, you don't have to
bring it. But then you remember this, well you're not obligated in
any part, so therefore, you know, so therefore you do have to
bring that. Let's see how it's argued. So that's point number one.
Wait, let's just I just want to finish the other argument so
you'll appreciate what this is about. Okay. So ונודע לו, v'noda lo,
I'm going to read it again, אבל נודע לו הקצירה של זדון
שבת ובשגגת מלאכות, avel noda lo haktsira shel zadon Shabbat u'vish'gagat melachot,
קצירה ktsira so you remember the קצירה ktsira first. קצירה גוררת קצירה
וטחינה שעמה, ktsira goreret ktsira v'techina she'ima, so the קצירה ktsira includes,
you know, the case this קצירה ktsira drags with it this קצירה
ktsira with the טחינה, techina, so you do not become obligated in
this קרבן because that's already some you've been somewhat obligated in part
of it. וטחינה שעמה וטחינה שכנגדה במקומה עומדת. v'techina she'ima v'techina she'k'negda
bim'koma omedet. But the other טחינה techina is not related and therefore
you would still be obligated in the other טחינה, techina, which so
let's see how אביי Abaye argues. אביי אמר טחינה נמי גוררת טחינה
שם טחינה אחת היא. Abaye amar techina nami goreret techina shem techina
achat hi. No, what אביי Abaye says is is that it works
two stage. That when you became obligated in this, although you're never
going to wind up bringing this because it's already included, but the
fact that this included טעינה teina means that when you become obligated
here in this טעינה, teina, you don't have to bring the טעינה
teina either. Okay, so until there it made sense, right? You could
say I've already been obligated in this קרבן, this קרבן is somewhat
overlaps my existing obligation, I don't have to bring it. But אביי
Abaye says, okay, but the fact that you would have brought this
means that when you get to the טעינה teina obligation, that's also
already included in this, and then this doesn't have to be brought
because of this. That's weird. So this is included in that, and
this doesn't have to be brought because it's somewhat overlapping with that.
Okay, and we will continue tomorrow to see this debate about what
things about these overlapping obligations. Good night.